The following content is
provided under a Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high -quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
So, are we ready
to go? Any questions on 1806 -5?
So it will be, as
I said before, a mixture
of linear algebra and math questions, along
with online
using the material.
OK,
so I'm, in this first
week or two,
reviewing
the highlights of linear algebra.
And I've reached
this point to remember,
well, so we, I just
said two
words about multiplying matrices
by using column times row
as a way to do it. And
I want to illustrate that by the
five key factorizations
of matrices.
OK,
so what are they? And
do you recognize them?
Everybody uses those letters. In
fact,
some of those letters, like LU or QR, would be the most used
MATLAB commands in linear algebra. So A equal LU, I'll maybe
say something I'll
develop today, but it's about elimination.
Solving linear systems.
So that's always the start of a linear
algebra course, but it will go fast here.
I just want to show you a different way to get to
L times U, lower triangular times upper triangular.
Probably you've seen that,
those
triangular matrices.
So do you
know what QR is? What's QR about?
Least squares. LEAST SQUARES
is the big application.
The factorization. So what kind of a matrix
gets that letter Q?
Orthogonal.
The columns are orthogonal.
Often orthonormal.
They're perpendicular
to each other.
And orthonormal means
they're unit vectors.
So Q often represents
a matrix
with orthonormal columns.
So we could say Graham -Schmidt, if you
want to remember a couple of old timers who
whose algorithm produces
Q and R.
How about
this one? This is really
a central one in math.
Pure math, applied math,
everywhere. Applications.
So S stands for symmetric. So this is a special factorization for
symmetric matrices. And you can see that it's symmetric. This lambda is the
diagonal eigenvalue matrix.
Always lambda
for eigenvalues.
Q is like that Q.
Different Q, of course.
That Q you can
find sort of just straightforward from
Graham -Schmidt. This Q has the eigenvectors.
So you don't
find eigenvectors without some extra work.
OK, so that's eigenvectors.
Yeah, so that would be
worth expanding.
So
here are the eigenvectors of the matrix S.
N of them normalized.
Here are the eigenvalues, lambda 1
to lambda n. And here are the eigenvectors
now transposed.
OK,
so remind me
of the great fact about,
two facts, I guess, one fact about the
eigenvalues and one fact about the eigenvectors.
This is like
an important fact and
statement in linear algebra.
What do we know about the eigenvectors? Oh,
well, I guess I'm giving it away.
The eigenvectors are?
Orthogonal.
That's very important. Makes the matrices,
well, they're beautiful
matrices.
They're the
kings of linear algebra.
Q's are the queens, in my opinion. Orthogonal matrices
are the queens of symmetric matrices are the kings.
So these are orthonormal eigenvectors. And
the key point, an important point
that's implicit here is there are n of them. There
is a complete set. The matrix can be diagonalized.
And those,
well, what's special
about the eigenvalues?
Other matrices could be Q lambda Q transpose.
But symmetric matrices are something
additional about lambdas.
They're all
real? They're all real.
So eigenvalues are real.
And eigenvectors
are orthonormal,
can be chosen orthonormal, can be chosen, I guess I have to say. OK,
good, good, good. Oh, now maybe I'll use that as an example of matrix
multiplication.
So let me just do that here.
Simple matrix multiplication, but it makes
the point.
Q lambda Q transpose.
OK, well, what was my
point about matrix multiplication?
Let me,
it really involved two matrices. Here I unfortunately have three.
So I'm going to have to squeeze lambda in with one of the Q's to
see it nicely as two matrices.
Shall I just do
that? Yeah, now I've made it two matrices.
That was easy.
OK,
now what's the rule?
In
the first notes, this was A and this was B.
And when you
multiply two matrices,
the rule is,
this is columns
of
Q lambda
times
rows of
Q transpose.
I'm multiplying columns
by rows. And so it's a column vector
times a row vector.
And that gives us a matrix.
So each,
and it's a special
matrix. So this is a column. This is a row.
And when I multiply n
by 1 times 1 by n, I get an n by n matrix.
And it's pretty special.
And what is the special fact about,
I'm sort of recalling from last time,
what's special about
a column times a row?
It's rank is special.
Its rank is 1.
Its column space,
well, the only column
around is this 1.
So all columns are
multiples of this guy.
All rows are
multiples of this guy,
as
we could see from an example. Shall I just
do an example?
1, 2 times 3, 4 to
take a random example.
So that would give us 3, 4,
6, 8.
And sure enough,
the columns are multiples of 1, 2. The rows
are multiples of 3, 4. And the rank is 1.
OK, so those
are the building blocks.
Now I want to build something.
So here we go.
So this is a sum of rank 1. Sum
of
rank 1.
Sum of
column
times row. So I take column 1 times row 1.
That's my first thing in the sum. So column 1 of that.
So you see I had to sneak the lambda in to have just two
factors.
So what's column
1 of q lambda? Oh, that's a good question.
So
column 1 of q is q1, the first eigenvector.
But now I'm multiplying
by this diagonal matrix.
Do you see in your mind
what's the first column of q lambda?
Just
think about that a second.
So here's,
we can steal any
little corner for a matrix.
OK, so here's q1.
And the rest of the columns.
And then here is lambda 1. And that's q lambda. So I'm putting those together.
And I'm asking, what's the first column of the answer? Can you see how
that works?
q1 lambda 1?
Yes, sorry? q1 lambda
1. q1 lambda 1, exactly.
That lambda 1 will multiply q1.
These other lambdas multiply later columns. So
the first column is lambda 1 times q1. Right.
So it's the
first guy, lambda 1 q1.
And then
the first row of this will be q1 transpose.
That's the first guy
in our sum of n things. And let me put the
next one and the last one.
Lambda 2 q2 q2 transpose.
And lambda n qn qn transpose.
That's really a nice way
to write,
to break up
the
product q lambda q transpose. This is called the spectral theorem. So
that's the symmetry. That's s. That's s there, is that. So we've broken up s
into rank 1 pieces.
That's like a constant theme.
And these
rank 1 pieces are quite special,
because they're symmetric.
q1 q1 transpose will be
symmetric.
And oh, so can we?
So that's just,
I follow the rule for multiplying matrices.
But maybe I
could just check that.
It's the right thing,
that it came out right.
So what do I mean by checking? I guess I'll
just check about s times q1. So look at s,
this thing, times the
first eigenvector. And what do I get?
OK.
So you'll like this.
So there's, I've split
up s into a sum of rank 1 pieces.
And that splitting is,
you see it all over.
It's really showing you what the pieces of the symmetric matrix are.
And now I'm just going to check that that's a correct formula for s.
So I'll multiply it by
q1. And I'm hoping to get the right thing.
And what do I actually get?
If I multiply this
whole business times q1,
I get lambda 1.
q1 transpose, that's the
first guy, times my q1.
Plus,
right?
I'm multiplying
s by q1. And this first term gave me that.
And what does the next
term give me? Put me out of my misery here.
I'm looking for this thing to simplify like
mad.
OK. So what's the
second term? When I multiply this guy
by q1,
what do I get? 0.
That's right.
That's what we want. And
when I multiply the last guy by q1,
I get 0, because
the q's are orthogonal.
So this is all I get.
And then,
so I don't need this plus anymore.
That's it.
And then
what can I do to improve
that little somewhat repetitive
formula for the answer? What do I want to do finally? I want
to remember that the q's are normalized. They're unit vectors.
So what does that tell me here?
q1 transpose. q1
transpose times q1. This is just 1.
That's what normalized means, that
the length squared is the length
of the vector squared.
And it's 1.
So I can cancel that term.
And I'm getting the right
answer. That's all I'm,
that's all this was about.
I was just checking
and wanted to see how
it would fall out. And it falls right out,
that this formula
is the correct matrix
S, because it's got the right eigenvectors.
q's. And it's got the right eigenvalues
lambda. So it's got to be the right matrix S.
Is that OK?
That's like a first example to see how this
splitting into rank 1's gives you back what you expect
easily enough. It gives you the information you expect.
It's a symmetric eigenvalue picture for
symmetric matrices. And we'll see it again.
Well, all five of these are big,
are important.
I don't know
if you know this one, but
it's going
to be a foundational factorization
for this
course and for all of data science.
Do you know its name?
So what does
it mean, first of all?
I'm going to comment on this. And
then we'll save it for a couple of weeks.
So this u is actually
an orthogonal matrix.
And so is v.
So it has
two orthogonal matrices.
So that's why
people called them u and
v rather
than q1 and q2, which
was too much to get subscripts.
So
orthogonal times diagonal times orthogonal.
Let me say orthogonal,
diagonal,
orthogonal.
And 1806 would, as of now, reach this
topic, because it's jumped up in importance.
And it's called?
Singular value. GILBERT STRANGER
WANSELL III. Singular value decomposition.
Well, those are
long words, so everybody calls it the SVD,
the singular
value decomposition.
The point is,
it works for every matrix,
rectangular matrices.
There's no
issue of, does it have enough eigenvectors
or not?
That's an issue here.
Well, it's an issue here.
Not every matrix has
got enough eigenvectors to make that work.
Every matrix,
that one works, because
instead of one set of
eigenvectors
it's got two matrices,
two different sets of singular vectors.
Oh, we'll see that.
That's important.
OK, so that's
really a quick overview
of fundamental factorizations.
And I'd like to say just another word about
elimination, a equal lu. And then we'll leave
it alone.
So elimination.
Yeah, do you remember that first
beginning of linear algebra when you're solving
Ax equal b, you do these row operations?
Can I just?
What I want to say is
all those row operations
that you do
are perfectly
expressed by l times u.
And so that's a key point in 18 .06, but I
have a different way to look at it.
So that's what
I wanted to show you.
I want to show you a sum of rank 1s, a row
times column. It fits in today.
So I'd just like to
see why does
a matrix,
invertible,
this is a square matrix now, an invertible.
And it factors, if all goes well with
elimination and the pivots are non -zero,
it factors into lower
triangular times upper triangular.
So that's a key step that MATLAB would do
with lu of a, would produce those two factors.
3 by 3, somebody not convinced totally by 2
by 2.
Let me do a 2
by 2. And then if you really want a 3 by 3,
I'll do it.
OK, here's 2 by 2. 2,
4,
3, 7. How's that?
OK.
So what is, yeah, so
let's remember
what elimination does.
It.
And then the question is,
express
that step
in matrix language.
And the right answer is
l times u.
So the right answer is that this
a is,
so I'll just erase that
letter u,
is l times u.
So what is l?
l is the lower triangular guy.
And
it has there the number that you used here.
And what was that? I subtracted 2
of that row from this. So I want a 2 there.
So that would be, I would call
that a multiplier. I multiplied row 1 by 2,
subtracted to get that 0. And for a 2 by 2
example, I was finished.
OK, now I want to see this.
So there is
l times u. It happened.
I would like to see how l times
u comes out of this row, column times row.
So let me start.
Let me think again.
So really, the
point of elimination,
what
was, why did we do this in the first place?
Because here we had
two coupled equations.
They were coupled
together. We couldn't solve them instantly.
That step of elimination reduced
me to,
down here in this
corner, one equation.
I've eliminated the first unknown
x
from the second equation.
The equation
is 0x plus 1y equal right -hand side. And I
solve it immediately.
OK,
so
how did I get to that
1 by 1 problem with these guys removed?
Well,
yeah,
just write, can I write here my
parallel way to think of it? And 2 by 2 is
pretty small, I admit. OK,
so I start with 2, 3, 4, 7.
I want to split it into, I want to get the
first row and column
in one piece.
Something goes there.
And the other piece is
something there.
OK,
that's what elimination
has done. It's taken the original matrix.
These are both rank 1.
So let's just, first of all, you could tell me what
goes in that blank space in the first rank 1 matrix.
Can I say this in words?
The first stage of elimination
pulls off
from A.
So A is some big matrix.
It pulls off from A.
It
takes account of the first column and row.
So it writes
A as, here we
go, as a first column,
say column 1, row 1,
plus
the easy part.
The easy part will be a matrix with all 0s there,
all 0s there. And here I have A2. Can I call it A2?
This is my
way now to think about what elimination is
really doing.
It's starting
with an n by n matrix.
It's pulling off
a rank 1 matrix,
which gets that column
and that row correct.
Whatever it has in here.
And then the rest of what's in there is A2.
Do you see that
we've done that here?
The first step got the first row and column
correct. And if it's rank 1, what number goes there?
6.
6 for that.
And then this is the rest. This is what we have one size
smaller to work on. And it looks like it was 7. 6 has been used.
1.
That's really,
I
want to think of this rank 1 matrix as the
first column of L times the first row of U.
And then
this guy is the second column of L
times the second row of U.
OK.
I haven't
presented this
proof in a class before.
And for 2 by 2, it's looking like overkill to me. I mean, like, why you
don't have to do all that deep thinking to get the pieces? But my idea is
that it gives the breakdown.
And this, of course,
is by our column times row rule, that's LU.
So we're starting with A.
And we're breaking it
up into LU,
where LU, the first
piece of LU is the first
column times row.
And then
the next pieces are the rest of the matrix.
And those get broken down the next
stage
of elimination would break.
If I had a 3 by 3,
this
stage peeled off the first column and row.
Then the next stage would peel off the second, the new second column
and row. And the third stage would have the third column and row, just
the last pivot. Does this make any sense to
you? You could email me and say
it's not that great.
But I think
it's to see that
the final result of
elimination is L times U.
It's a little magic in
seeing what you're doing. And I think this is
a way to see what you're doing, that you're
peeling off a first part
to leave
a second part like that.
Then the second part, you would peel
off the second column times the second row,
maybe divide by the pivot to make it correct. And that would put something
in the rest of the box. And then A3 would be the rest of that box.
OK, I'm stopping here.
I'm glad you let me do 2 by 2,
since I
see that 3 by 3 would have ruined the day.
Yeah, OK.
A question or let
me pause for a minute.
So I've talked about
these factorizations.
This one we won't see
again. This one we will see big time.
And this one we will. And this one we will. Yeah, yeah. 2,
3, and 5 are the ones that we're really going to see a lot of
questions or thoughts.
OK, I guess
I want to tell you now to complete today's
and moving forward in
this subject,
the fundamental theorem
of linear algebra.
The fundamental theorem
OK, ready for that?
Or you may have seen it
already, because
it's like the highlight of
this subject,
of the basic
ideas in this subject.
And then
maybe I can, after I tell you that theorem,
people around the world
have given me homework problems to do.
Now, you would think any sensible professor would never
do those problems. Like, he would say, it's your problem.
But I get carried
away, and I solve them sometimes.
So one came from India last week, and it involved the fundamental theorem
of linear algebra. Whoever teaching it there really was on the ball.
And well,
I'll tell you that problem after
the fundamental theorem.
OK, fundamental theorem.
It's about four subspaces.
So I invented the name
for fundamental subspaces.
So can I
list the four subspaces?
Fundamental subspaces.
Well, we
know one of them already,
the column space.
So
for a matrix.
We're given a matrix A
that's m by n of rank R.
That's our
normal starting point.
So what are those four subspaces? And how
are they related? And what's their dimension?
And what those
are key facts.
OK, we already
know the column space.
Column space of a matrix.
And actually,
we already know the row space of a matrix.
And we have the notation
for that column space of A transpose.
And what is the dimension?
So that was the key point in the first lecture. Anybody who missed
the first lecture should go back to the notes of 1 .1 for the
for the thinking that
goes into the dimension equals what?
Which of
those three numbers do I want to?
Is the dimension of
the column space R?
R. And what can I
say about R right away compared to m and n?
Yeah, less or equal.
I
couldn't have more independent columns than
I have columns.
N columns.
So R of them are independent.
So R is somewhere less or equal, hopefully
equal to n.
What about the dimension
of the row space?
How many independent rows has the matrix
got? R. R, thank you. That's a great fact
with a new proof last
time in section 1 .1,
that those
have the same dimension.
Same dimension,
which is,
you think,
OK, you look at a simple example, it's true.
But if you're given a matrix that's 50 by 100,
really the fact that those
100 columns have the same number of independent
ones as those 50 rows, that's great.
OK, now the
other spaces are the null space.
Of the matrix,
n of a.
And just to
make everything naturally symmetric,
the null space of
a transpose.
Those are the last two.
Those are the four
fundamental subspaces,
which you've seen. And they're even on the
cover of the linear algebra textbook.
OK,
so what's the null space?
The set of vectors that solve A equals 0.
It's a set of solutions to AX equals 0. Right.
Null space
is
all solutions
to AX equals 0.
So the null space has these vectors in it,
the x's.
The null
space isn't taken from the matrix.
The row space
and the column space,
those numbers are
sitting in the matrix.
The null space and the
null space of A transpose
are solutions to
the word null is
reflecting the fact that that's a 0.
And that's what makes
it a space.
Now, let
me just ask you to think again.
What's implied when I use the word space, a
space of vectors?
Closed under addition. GILBERT
STRANGSKIY ANDERSON III I can add, yeah.
So I can do the most important operations of linear
algebra in that space. I can add two vectors.
Here, let me just add
them. So here, I'll have a vector x.
And let me say another one,
a vector y.
Then
I
do addition. I follow the rules.
I see that this
can be written as
AX plus y is 0 plus 0.
So what have I learned?
I've learned that if
x is in the null space
and y is in the null space, then x plus y.
So the
null space is, as you said, closed, meaning
I don't go outside it. If x is in it and y is in it, then the sum
is in it. And similarly, from AX equals 0, I get to A times C. BX
equals 0.
Just multiply by C, by
a number C.
So those two facts,
that means I
can do linear algebra.
I can multiply by numbers,
and I can add.
In other words, I can take linear
combinations. That's what you do with vectors.
And the point is,
if I take combinations
of two null space guys,
I'm still in the null space.
So that's the point of
the null space.
And so now part of the fundamental theorem
is to figure out how many
independent vectors
are in the null space.
How many independent solutions does that system
of equations have? So that will be the dimension.
And I have to ask you what it is.
Let me draw a picture while you're
thinking about those spaces.
It's fantastic to
have these beautiful, clean boards.
OK, so here is my
picture of the row space.
Rows, that's the column
space of A transpose.
And here is my picture of
the null space,
N of A.
And that's the
solutions to AX equals 0.
And why have I put
these two together and
these two together?
So the other pair will be the column space,
C of A.
And
null space of A transpose.
So there are the four spaces.
Their relationship is
the fundamental theorem
of linear algebra.
So first of all,
what?
So I have an m by n matrix.
So that tells me that my rows, a typical row, has n components,
right? I look at an m by n matrix. Let's do a 2 by 3 matrix.
So if I look at the row space,
this is m and this is n.
So I see 3.
The rows have length 3.
And of course,
they multiply the x's,
which also have
length 3. x1, x2, x3.
That's why these are together,
because they're both in
n -dimensional space.
Then why are these together?
Because the columns
are in two -dimensional
space, for this example.
And the null space of A transpose would be
just two components, like y1, y2, to give 0's.
So do you see that
this is R? These guys are in Rm.
So that's the first.
Like, get things straight.
Two spaces in Rn,
two spaces in Rm.
Now,
what am I going to ask about these spaces?
I guess I already started asking and didn't
wait for an answer.
They're dimension.
So this has dimension R.
And what's
the dimension? How many?
This is really such a key fact.
If I have
m equations, Ax equals 0.
And if R of
those equations are independent,
how many solutions?
So the dimension of this space is going to
tell me how many solutions to
m equations, but really only R,
genuine, independent equations,
in
this
system Ax equals 0.
How many?
So can I ask the question again?
In terms of m and n and R.
So I really have R equations.
If I look at Ax equals 0, it looks like m,
separate equations.
But m minus R of those are just copies or combinations
of others. So there are R independent equations.
So how many have I got?
And
that's what I'm going
to write in here. Yeah.
So yes.
So x has n components.
And there are real
active equations that
they have to satisfy.
And that leaves n minus R.
That's the key point.
That there
are n components of x,
n unknowns, n unknowns.
And there are R constraints,
independent constraints.
So those n get, if I want to satisfy those constraints, that knocks
out dimension R and leaves n minus R. So that's the dimension here.
And the beauty of
the count
is that those two numbers add up
to n.
Everybody's accounted for.
So you have a row space and a piece in the
null space. And those two pieces
give you back the vector.
Do you see that? That's just nice that the numbers come
out right. And of course, they come out right here too.
You could say, just transpose the matrix and write the
same thing again. What's the dimension of the column space?
Equals the other column space of the
matrix. The matrix has dimension R, right?
And the row,
this guy is left out of some linear algebra
books, as if it doesn't belong.
But
isn't it clear that without it,
everything
is only 3 quarters done?
We have to have this
guy. And its dimension is m minus R. Yeah.
That count is just
for A transpose what this count was for A.
Yeah. So we've got those dimensions, R and
n minus R,
R and m minus R.
Yeah.
You'll have
known this, but we need to
see it once again
in 2018 before we start using it.
Now,
is that the fundamental theorem?
All to a . No.
There is another piece to the fundamental
theorem, which is sort of, you could say,
the geometry.
Here I have a subspace.
Here I have a subspace
of this big
n -dimensional space.
So I visualize those subspaces as some kind
of a plane, an R -dimensional plane,
and an n minus
R -dimensional plane.
And I want
to see, how are those two planes connected?
How
are those two planes connected?
And let me get a
blank piece of the
board to remember the final step.
So we've got dimensions
R and n minus R,
and then over
here, R and m minus R.
OK.
This is for
the rows.
This is for the null space.
So this has
the rows in it. This
has the null, the solutions to Ax equals 0.
What is
the beautiful geometry?
How
do you visualize those
two spaces?
How do you visualize?
Let me take an example.
Let A be 1, 2, 4,
2, 4, 8. Sorry about that. It's kind of
a hoax. You see it's a hoaxed up example.
So this is 2 by 3.
So there, n is 3.
What's in the null
space of this matrix?
The rows
are dependent. There's only one
independent row. The columns are dependent.
Every column is a multiple of 1, 2. It's a
rank 1 matrix.
OK. What about its row space has dimension
1,
and its null
space has dimension 2.
So because n minus R will be 2.
So I'm looking
for a couple of vectors
that both give 0.
I believe there
are, I think I've only got one independent
row there. So I should
be able to find two different vectors that
solve Ax equals 0.
So what's the
solution to Ax equals 0?
0 minus 2, 1. 0
minus 2, 1.
Yeah, that works.
And what's an
independent solution?
4, 0.
Don't throw me off. 4, 0 and?
Minus 1. Minus 1.
Yeah, that looks good.
That looks good.
And then the claim is that every solution
would be a combination of those two.
And that this
is how many there are.
And now it's the geometry I'm completing. So we have like
two minutes left in this lecture. You just have to tell
me what's the relation between these guys in
the row space and that guy in the null space?
What's the relation between the
rows of A and the solutions to Ax equals 0?
If
you saw that vector and that vector, well,
A times x is 0. Now, so
what does that tell us? What do we see for
the relation
between 1, 2, 4 and 0 minus 2, 1? They're
orthogonal. They are orthogonal. Terrific.
Yes.
Orthogonal, I test by
the dot product 0 minus 4, 4 add to 0.
Yes.
So the,
and that's a completely general fact. When I look at Ax
equals 0, it's telling me that x is orthogonal to the rows.
Do you see that?
Just to
put it in again here.
If I look at Ax,
A has a bunch of rows.
x has one column.
And I
get 0. That's the point of the null space.
And that equation is just saying
that row 1 is orthogonal,
because that's the dot
product of row 1 with x.
So here's row 1. Row 2,
row 3, and row 4 with x.
The rows with x.
And I get 0s.
So
the point is then these
two spaces are at 90 degree angles.
That's really a neat
picture of the four subspaces.
And these two are for
the same reason at 90 degree angles, often
m dimensional space.
So that's
the fundamental theorem
of linear algebra, to
see that the dimensions come out right
and the geometry comes out right. Yeah. And
then now, next time,
following the notes, and I
have a few more copies of the one handout,
we'll move on quickly next week to
eigenvalues and positive definite matrices.
But
really linear algebra, moving on.